<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-31T11:33:17-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">svmihar’s scribble</title><subtitle>ideas left unsaid</subtitle><entry><title type="html">5 second style copy</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/deep-learning/2019/11/01/style-transfer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 second style copy" /><published>2019-11-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/deep-learning/2019/11/01/style-transfer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/deep-learning/2019/11/01/style-transfer.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;wkwk, ikut conference itu feeding ego doang, existentialism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ah masa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;neural-style-transfer-a-pycon-story&quot;&gt;neural style transfer, a pycon story.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;just-why&quot;&gt;just why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;well,  i’m in a rut of doing nlp stuff, finetuning parameters, climbing the hills and valleys of errors, I needed &lt;del&gt;pelarian&lt;/del&gt; something to do without all these metrics. Looking at the empty walls of my rooms, I decided to search for posters to stick on the walls, making my room much &lt;em&gt;more enjoyable to look at.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;searching for the fittest within my preferences takes forever to finish, I constraint myself not to do manual design just ol’ plain seeing and printing, and this print is only and gonna be the only one in the world. I want it to be &lt;em&gt;unique and easy&lt;/em&gt;! This narrows to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;band posters: meh, too mainstream, it’ll take work to make it “my style”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;film posters: i am too volatile to love one particular movies, thus only got the budget for printing one.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quote posters: you got to be kidding me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;motivational quote posters: 🙃&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;dian sastro poster&lt;/del&gt;
So I still got some viable solutions like:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;print a film photograph
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;cost more money, &lt;em&gt;maklum anak kosan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;edit a photo to look like it was taken from an analog film camera
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this is basically a filter.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from the filter solution, this looks like the one. I was kinda happy but not satisfied because I’m not a very skilled photographer and not many of my photos amazes me. So I decided to have a different approach with a 3D render, recreating one of my photograph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long story short it is too much of a hassle. Props to you all 3D digital artist with all those octane rendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I saw a tweet from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vngnc&quot;&gt;@vngc&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;it’s a tweet about neural style transfer, unfortunately he deleted his twitter ☹️&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;STYLE TRANSFER!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - this is what I am looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This got me hooked! well I can recreate those stuff, it’s only a CNN on a picture!  I just needed a painting style and apply it to the photograph of my choosing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is surely a “filter” on steroids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how&quot;&gt;how?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/s7WKTmA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
so how does one copy a pattern of brush strokes, the pressure of the brushes to the canvas and the beautiful colors from the original paintings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;let me tell you: edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;edges is what makes the subject different from the backgorund, contrast in between edges is what defines one brush stroke to the other. Edges is what  It’s the edges that we are looking to copy! So how does one copy “an edge” to other image?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;now by getting the edges, recreating the edges how does a human can copy a style? well you don’t we leave it to the computationally superior guys to simulate it. the computers. well the computers don’t know what’s an edge is and what’s a picture, what’s a pattern, so  they needed a good “kinda look alike edges” from the human world to the computer’s world. How? Representation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To obtain a representation of a style of an image, how does one define an edge? an &lt;strong&gt;edge is what makes a texture&lt;/strong&gt;.  The information, or the “edges” inside the texture is what we’re trying to look for exactly. Then by representing it as an array a computer can easily simulate it in a scale that human can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does the computer sees exactly? &lt;strong&gt;pixel values&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because an image is just a bunch of bunch of bunch of numbers in an arrays with the value of red, green and blue values (r,g,b,a).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, getting the all this texture information how to distinguish between the texture that we are trying to capture and the wholesome arrangement of the image? we’re trying to copy the brush strokes not the subject of the image right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The representation of the styles is what we will store to an n^th dimension space. Therefore to capture its textual information, this “space” is where the VGG19 comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, the layers in VGG19 will try to search the “correlation”  between result of the layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it will try to deconstruct the input image by downsampling it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally the resulting correlation feature space or the texture we’re trying to copy will match the style to the downsampled image we’re trying to paste our texture to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these processes are what we’re trying to create resulting a new texture information to the input image, and discarding the arrangement of the pixel from the styled image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That my friend, is what we’re looking for. The separation of content and style representation.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/GSh8hqI.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optimizing-the-loss&quot;&gt;optimizing the loss&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i know making something good means having a good metric to compare to, but this metric we’ll be using is actually the metric that measures the distance between the generated image, to the content and style image. 
How do you measure the distance between images? gram matrix. 
Before going to the gram matrix we need to clarify what are the losses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;content loss: means the difference between the “content” in the content image to the generated image.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;style loss: means the difference between the “style” in the style image to the generated image. 
How do you measure “content” and “style”? like all mathematicians, to measure a distance we need two points to measure on. We map the content image to a hilbert space using the VGG19’s feature layer, making it a vector, then map the style image and generated image also. These vectors can be measured from the distances, seeing it as how far is it different from each other. 
The gram matrix is the result of the inner product of the vectors. This actually shows the spatial correlation between the images. Think of it as a historgram. It doesn’t measure specific pixel to pixel or a location of the images. It calculate only the feature distribution that we wanted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feature-extractors-x-transfer-learning&quot;&gt;feature extractors x transfer learning.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite. Transfer learning is used to extract what you call a texture information on an image. How do you extract it is by mapping the “patterns” of an image to a feature layer. The Think of this transfer learning as a baseline of our model, the model itself (VGG19), is a CNN architecture which used 15 million images from the ImageNet dataset, and trained on a 138 million parameters that uses 5 convolutional layers.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/PGhEo49.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
By using VGG’s pretrained models, our model doesn’t need to learn from scratch and saving a lot of time and space, by only fine tuning the top layers, on what we wanted it to output (generated image). Both weight and biases from the pretrained model is what the feature extractors are. Diffrentiating which is which, edges, patterns, textures, brush strokes, colors, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;using pytorch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generated a white noise for the generated image&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adding style and content from the extracted features from both the content and style image&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;backprop and gradient descent step optimized using L-BFGS to find the loss function score&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iterate till satisified with result
The L-BFGS is just a work around on a smaller GPU capability. 
My implementation on this is actually stack 10 scripts on each other, changing its initiation image to the output image from the previous script output. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s5.gifyu.com/images/Webp.net-gifmaker-3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
to produce image, from the 10 scripts:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using google colab: 3045 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using gradient’s p5000: 971s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-implementation&quot;&gt;other implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maps, on maps
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s5.gifyu.com/images/Webp.net-gifmakerf00bd7504b5fa743.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;painting on paintings
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s5.gifyu.com/images/Webp.net-gifmaker-1a2f653dc9c5ad9ee.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parting-words&quot;&gt;parting words&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am deeply honored to be invited to be the speaker on pycon indo 2019 about this however, to make the project “demo-able” i made several improvements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cycleGAN&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fast-style-neural-trasnfer
Both are a pretty good “feature extractors” with way different implementation to each other. But both has a pretty good serializeable file that I can use to generate a new image without training it again and again. Creating CLI is cool and stuff, but I decided to take a step further by making a telegram bot, try it out while its still online &lt;a href=&quot;t.me/styletransferbot&quot;&gt;@styletransferbot&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot of things about the GANs, making art with deep learning. Sometimes learning machine learning is all about metrics: getting good prediction, less error, less biased towards certain things, more reliable and good black box models, what I get from this is programming in the society should be changed from a tool for industries to something more! something that helps us to be more expressive as humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop making weapons of math destructions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I guess decorating my room got hell bent to a long hole of optimization problem eh.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;deep-learning&quot;]" /><summary type="html">wkwk, ikut conference itu feeding ego doang, existentialism</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/s7WKTmA.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/s7WKTmA.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">\\darkness</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/talk/2019/03/05/workshop-data-mining-di-UB.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="\\darkness" /><published>2019-03-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-03-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/talk/2019/03/05/workshop-data-mining-di-UB</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/talk/2019/03/05/workshop-data-mining-di-UB.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;if you can’t explain something in simple terms, you don’t understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/bffsi4O.png&quot; alt=&quot;ub means universitas brawijaya, loved the unbraw abbreviation tho.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-v1&quot;&gt;update v1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thisismetis/dsp&quot;&gt;this kind of workshop ternyata takes several days, bahkan sampe dibikin bootcamp. i cramp it into 3 hours.&lt;/a&gt; approach nya sangat noob proof. kalo ada kesempatan lagi i’ll definitely use this as a precourse material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;kok-bisa&quot;&gt;kok bisa&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;awalnya gak nyangka diajak buat ikutan seminar. Diajak ikutan berarti asumsi awal adalah &lt;strong&gt;mengikuti&lt;/strong&gt; seminar tentang data mining, bukan mengisi kan, karena dirasa saya masih perlu banyak belajar jadi saya memutuskan secara langsung gak pake mikir buat ikutan. Ternyata &lt;em&gt;tidak&lt;/em&gt;
disini diajak ikutan adalah menjadi pembicara. Awal ngeh itu ketika disuruh bikin penjelasaan algoritma SVM, Kmeans dan heiarchical. Ketika ditanya buat apa, ternyata disuruh ngisi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt; &lt;strong&gt;hint #0&lt;/strong&gt;. cara menaklukan hewan buas seperti mengimplementasikan dan membuat sebuah algoritma ternyata berbeda dengan menaklukan orang-orang yang ingin belajar.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hint #1&lt;/strong&gt;. it’s not something that i really enjoy. it’s like debugging an app, but instead of one app, you’re debugging a whole class of errors. Like playing chess, but instead of 1 opponent, you’re actually playing with several people at the same time. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR;&lt;/strong&gt; simpler learning material, approach sesuai dengan background dari pesertanya or having a pre-course material given before the workshop, and having an evalution metrics whatever metric type.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;lessons-given&quot;&gt;lesson(s) given&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of course python. pake sklearn, scipy, pandas dan numpy. oh matplotlib juga. should’ve gone with seaborn tho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;super basic sih, mainly about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;machine learning algorithms
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;clustering: kmeans, agglomerative, dendogram&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;classification: svm with linear, rbf and polynomial kernels&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exploratory data analysis
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;making sense of data with pearson coefficient&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mencari korelasi antar feature di kolom&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data visualization
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;basics of matplotlib.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;disini sebenernya lebih kepada showcasing ketimbang mengajakarkan cara membuatnya. dimana implementasi algoritma dijelaskan dengan lancar tapi memvisualisasikannya agak “cacat” karena tidak terbiasa mengotak-atik sebuah visualisasi. i should’ve go with seaborn. but i went with matplotlib instead (i’m assuming they are aware of matplotlib because it’s literally derived from the matlab plot library. &lt;em&gt;they don’t.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;oh iya sama beberapa subtle “hints” of github. dimana resource sharing disini tinggal ambil dari github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;lesson(s) learned&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;should-have-gone-with-more-structurized-material&quot;&gt;should have gone with more structurized material&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;bukan beberapa ide yang “mashed together” menjadi pembelajaran, ternyata gak belajar. malah error debugging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shouldve-gone-with-the-handout-type&quot;&gt;should’ve gone with the handout type.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you can read the comments, people without any programming background find it hard to see comments in code. use jupyternotebook markdown instead. have some latex to type the equations. (&lt;em&gt;i did &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/svmihar/seminar-ub/blob/master/Seminar Data Mining Matematika UB.ipynb&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, but still hard to grasp i guess.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;longer&quot;&gt;longer.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;coding workshop is not mere 3-4 hours of talking. it’s mainly error debugging. saya berdiri di depan dengan asumsi semua sudah nyaman dengan python. ternyata tidak. yang terjadi pada saat itu adalah saya ngetik sendiri yang lainnya hanya mereka karena saya terlalu cepat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-clear-boilerplates-noob-proof&quot;&gt;make clear boilerplates (noob proof).&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;boilerplates diciptakan untuk mempercepat proses yang redundant. bukan menciptakan kebingungan yang lebih. sebebernya boilerplate nya sudah ada hanya saja akan tetapi dataset yang disediakan sudah terlalu advanced untuk membuat proof of concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clear-backgoround-about-the-peserta&quot;&gt;clear backgoround about the peserta.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cukup menjadi masalah karena boilerplate yang disediakan bukan untuk non coder. jadinya ya berantakan. akhirnya malah saya sendiri yang asik di depan sementara pesertanya hanya planga plongo tidak mengerti apa yang terjadi pada datanya. 
bahkan melihat &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install sklearn&lt;/code&gt;  saja sudah merasa menjadi programmer. 
okay welcome to the darkside then i guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-practice-on-public-speaking&quot;&gt;more practice on public speaking.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;seharusnya sudah tau di depan itu mau ngobrol tentang apa. terlalu advanced topiknya? jadikan diskusi. terlalu gampang topik di depan? jadikan game. skill inilah sebenernya yang bisa “adapt vastly” kepada penontonnya. memang si speaker yang memandu si penontonnya tapi penontonnya harus tau tujuan akhir bagaimanapun proses menuju tujuan akhirnya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-some-music&quot;&gt;have some music.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s not a damn test. relax. buat beberapa games untuk memecah suasana, memperkecil jarak dari penonton ke pembicara.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/7JBB38F.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;improvements&quot;&gt;improvements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;suitable-internet-connection&quot;&gt;suitable internet connection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i know it’s indonesia assume bad internet at all times. but come on. at this scale the facilitator should’ve had priavte fast speed internet connection. you think datasets and api calls are small bandwith stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pre-course-material&quot;&gt;pre course material.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;have the peserta learned up, jadi ketika diterangkan bisa lebih ngeh dengan apa yang tidak dimengerti dan mengerti apa yang tidak diketahui.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pre-test-post-test-cycle&quot;&gt;pre-test-post-test cycle.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;biar tau apakah ada improvement sebelum dan sesudah workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;longer-1&quot;&gt;longer.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;seriously. 3-4 hours of pengantar data science itu tidak cukup. i’m trying bootcamp style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hotel&quot;&gt;hotel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the guest house is nice tho. i guess calling it a hotel itu lebih pantes. but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/xuTfB2X.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;PLEASE INSTALL A GOOD WIFI. YOU’RE NOT A HOTEL UNLESS YOU HAD A GOOD WIFI&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;parting-words&quot;&gt;parting words&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i guess the quote by richard feynman above summarizes it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">if you can’t explain something in simple terms, you don’t understand it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/7JBB38F.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/7JBB38F.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">tutorial memanggil setan dengan bilangan kompleks</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/music/2019/02/28/tutorial-memanggil-setan-dengan-bilangan-kompleks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="tutorial memanggil setan dengan bilangan kompleks" /><published>2019-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-02-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/music/2019/02/28/tutorial-memanggil-setan-dengan-bilangan-kompleks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/music/2019/02/28/tutorial-memanggil-setan-dengan-bilangan-kompleks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;last update: 31-05-2020&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;podcast adalah background noise, karena jalan kaki tanpa podcast adalah tahu tek tanpa petis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;app&quot;&gt;app&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the only app I use since the beginning is castbox.fm, karena ada beberapa fitur yang cukup krusial untuk menjadi app podcast yang memenuhi batas bawah standar saya. hehe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;web, android, ios supported&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;time syncing
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wherever whenever whatever device yang saya pake, bisa lanjut where i left off.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;offline support
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this is indonesia. expect bad internet at all times. 
i’m trying spotify because of the community but no offline support except if you’re subbed to the premium which i’m not because i’m broke af. so no spotify for me. 
other contenders are google podcast and pocket cast, but google podcast didn’t have any linux love :( and pocket cast is just too much hassle to try.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i’m sticking to &lt;a href=&quot;https://castbox.fm/&quot;&gt;castbox.fm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;things-that-i-listen-to&quot;&gt;things that i listen to:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;programming&quot;&gt;programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mainly topics about coding, and tech startups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk Python to me: u python? u listen this. &lt;strong&gt;nuff said&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Release&lt;/em&gt; weekly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;artifical intelligence podcast by lex fridman: super formal, super concise. 80% cocok dengan podcast ini, tamunya itu rang orang yang otaknya diatasnya atasnya langit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;python bytes: dev to dev conversation, suka bahas python packages yang menarik&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Skeptic: data science-centric, banyak bahas paper yang menarik, host nya juga ikutan menarik soalnya suka berantem karena suami istri (katanya berantem itu biasa diambil dari distribusi gaussian)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a16z Podcast: bahas startup from groundup, technical side, both dark side and gray side lol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practical ai: ini persepektif non engineer ke ai in general sih, jadi bahasanya mudah dimengerti untuk manusia biasa seperti saya&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Techpoint charlie: bahas roles yang baru maupun lama yang ada di perusahaan engineering centric. suka ngundang executives dari FAANGs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;command line heroes: bahas sejarah disruption di tech, how quirky those old scientist and engineers that shape up tech world today.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;darknet diaries: digital murder stories (yang di murder bits and bytes serta career POI nya kok, bukan manusiannya)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;twiml ai: sampai dengan blog ini di tulis masih gak tau singkatan dari TWIML itu apa, tapi ini banyak bahasa topik conference gede di NLP, CV, yah seputar machine learning lah&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;SuperDataScience: this is some career stuff talking.&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;gak dengerin lagi karena lebih mirip meditasi ini podcast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Syntax: orang gaul-nya javascript and web dev in general. Not only programming covers up little details about programming I tend to brush off. Good stuff if you’re still learning and no bias around lgbt.&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;done with this boi, karena front-end aint worth it&lt;/strong&gt;a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;productivity&quot;&gt;productivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mainly soft skill buat programmer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developer Tea: super singkat like 10 minutes podcast. Good when listening when having coffee, discusses how normal people see programmers and how to “act” like a ninja/rockstar/[buzzword_here] programmer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Accidental Creative: practical everyday practices on working professionally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Beyond To do list: time management stuff, self financial management juga dibahas&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;bikin to do list mulu, dikerjain kagak. engga deh. udah move on dari belajar ginian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;life&quot;&gt;life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;entah kenapa udah males. haha. jadi banyak pivot ke entertaiment, atau easy listening aja&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freakonomics radio: reality check. radio dengan penjelasan kondisi sekarang yang gak bertele-tele&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explain the universe: podcast halu, suka nanya pertanyaan yang bikin hMMhmhmmmmMMMmm, contoh: gimana kalo matahari jadi 2x lebih besar, konstanta paling konstan di dunia. halu suer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;corridor cast: salah satu vfx di LA, orangnya seru mirip engineer tapi vfx artist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crime-and-murder-stories&quot;&gt;crime and murder stories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;drama itu lebih seru kalo nyata. imo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once upon a crime: biasanya unsolved, leaves audience with a task at the of the podcast.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;murder squad: the infamous golden state killer capturer (?), penjelasannya lengkap SOP kalo ketangkep,ditangkep mencari. mayan membuka mata dari persepektif polis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;crime junkie: bizarre past crimes and murders, informasinya lengkap kalo dari podcast ini.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;small town dicks: kejadian-kejadian kecil yang biasanya gak dimuat di majalah tapi masih menarik buat jadi bahan pembicaraan dan pemikiran ini.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;disgraceland: tidak perlu dipungkiri, musisi, entertaiment, dan crimes itu gak jauh-jauh amat diukur dari cara beroperasinya&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Become More Compelling: ini seperti buku ‘How to Win Friends and Influence People’ tapi adaptasi abad 21-nya.&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;self help, gak dengerin gituan lagi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Real Talk Radio: Issues yang banyak taboo di masyarakat, seperti feminisme, male privelege dan teman2nya deh. seru kalo lagi real drama yang bisa disdiskusikan dengan significan other (biar gak gosip mulu)&lt;/del&gt;&lt;strong&gt;self help&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Coder radio: mengenal programmer2 di bidang lain kayak, devOps, Cloud Engineer, Site Reliability, dan banyak banget. Bahasannya juga ringan seputar programming news&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;lupa kenapa dihapus, dirasa sudah tidak penting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;The Skeptics Guide to universe: literally bahas semuanya tapi pake pembuktian. intresting stuff here&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;bikin ngantuk soalnya pembahasannya suka kepotong2 dan gak linear jadi suka lupa lagi bahas apa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;couples-and-relationship&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;couples and relationship&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;- Candy and Casey’s Couple Therapy: They’re abrupt honesty makes my heart melt. too much freedom is bad tapi seru kalo bareng sama teman sejiwa.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;- Arif and Tipang podcast: i need to be present. pandangan pasangan millenial sama yang 40 tahun nikah kan beda. enak punya spectrum yang luas tentang relationship. walaupun kalo yang ini banyak cringe-nya (&lt;em&gt;pencitraan&lt;/em&gt;) tapi ya gpp, anggap aja contoh yang buruk&lt;/del&gt;  &lt;strong&gt;pengetahuan terbaik adalah dari pengalaman.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;music.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/3CwC84dkr2lYpLOuoU0HA3&quot;&gt;lagu buat ngoding&lt;/a&gt; | 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6mNVYuiMOiwBVgRSvImVtv&quot;&gt;lagu buat lari&lt;/a&gt; | 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/3C1zkGnnqr4xKhNtVtOLUD&quot;&gt;lagu buat baca tengah malem&lt;/a&gt; |
&lt;del&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/playlist/6J5HH7RGdrc73vO9myjaZt&quot;&gt;lagu buat cangkruk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;udah gak nyangkruk, mending tidur&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;parting-words&quot;&gt;parting words&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;music is like complex number equation, it shows what real state cannot explain. 
I walk a lot that’s why I fill my ‘kekosongan’ with all these voices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">last update: 31-05-2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/O30KQpz.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/O30KQpz.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">mengenai produktifitas</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/produktivitas/2018/08/01/mengenai-produktifitas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="mengenai produktifitas" /><published>2018-08-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-08-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/produktivitas/2018/08/01/mengenai-produktifitas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/produktivitas/2018/08/01/mengenai-produktifitas.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;ngapain aja sih&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;jadi kamu mengejar, atau dikejar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setiap hari, selalu ada saja prioritas dalam hidup, check box yang menunggu
untuk dicentang, hal yang harus dirapikan dan masalah yang harus diselesaikan.
Seluruh tenaga digunakan untuk berpikir di luar kotak, mencari sebuah solusi
efisien nan elegan. Tapi apa betul manusia hanya hidup untuk menjadi
interdependen dengan sekelilingnya?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayangkan dari sibuknya mengejar deadline tiap hari dengan menggunakan internet
dan listrik suatu saat diambil dalam sekejap. Apakah pekerjaanmu mendefinisikan
jati dirimu? atau jati dirimu yang mendefinisikan pekerjaanmu?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kala itu deadline foto pre wedding seorang client sudah terlambat satu hari,
seperti biasa saya di marahi bos saya karena tidak sesuai deadline. Alasan
“mandek kreatifitas” menjadi solusi. “Belum dapet mood (suasana dalam gambar)
yang bagus ni buat mas ini nih”. Sampai akhirnya terpaksa meniru mood dari
produksi lain. Sampai pada suatu masa dimana seluruh foto selesai di edit harus
di render dan, mati lampu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebagai seorang yang berat di otak kiri saya memikirkan 3 solusi. Saya ke warkop
langganan saya dimana ada pasokan listrik yang memadai dan internet yang lebih
dari cukup kecepatannya untuk upload, atau ke lab komputasi dimana semuanya ada
dan tinggal colok kabel LAN saja dan bisa offload render di komputer lab atau
menunggu. Lekas saya mandi dan bersiap untuk ke Lab karena terkait masalah
ekonomi saya memutuskan untuk upload di lab. Seolah alam tidak ingin saya pergi,
hujan pun datang, jas hujan dipinjam. Seolah tidak ingin membuang duit untuk
menyewa GrabCar saya memutuskan untuk menunggu dalam gelap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perasaan tidak melakukan apa-apa seolah tak berdaya tidak dapat “produktif demi
interdependensi manusia” memnpm buat saya berpikir. Apakah manusia disebut berguna
ketika dia bekerja untuk orang lain? Apakah manusia menemukan jati dirinya
ketika diakui oleh orang lain? Lantas orang lain itu siapa untuk mendefinisikan
jati diri kita? Apakah kita dapat menemukan jati diri kita dari kehampaan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dari sini perasaan dimana tidak dapat melakukan apa-apa itu sedikit demi sedikit
membuat saya teringat dulu. Ketika kewajiban hanyalah untuk diri pribadi,
tanggung jawab tidak sebesar dan sedewasa diri ini, belum mempunyai makna untuk
berguna bagi sesama, interdependensi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jadi apakah interdependensimu didefinisikan dari pekerjaan mu? atau dari
kehampaan kamu dapat tetap berguna bagi lingkunganmu?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rasa hampa ini membuat saya bergidik ngeri akan rasanya menuruti kedangingan
manusia untuk menunda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a quick cheer to a standing ovation, clap to show how much you enjoyed this
story.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/vNWNYSL.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/vNWNYSL.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">bifurkasi tukang parkir.</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/not-important/2018/01/01/bifurkasi-kang-parkir.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="bifurkasi tukang parkir." /><published>2018-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/not-important/2018/01/01/bifurkasi-kang-parkir</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/not-important/2018/01/01/bifurkasi-kang-parkir.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;tidak apa-apa direndahkan yang penting tidak rendahan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;yang satu recehan dari saku mobil, yang satu dari saku pajak!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/x8Jz1YN.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/klkvBBW.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;not-important&quot;]" /><summary type="html">tidak apa-apa direndahkan yang penting tidak rendahan.</summary></entry></feed>